Finding Aid for Michael Staebler Papers 1872-1934
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Michael Staebler Papers 1872-1934
Staebler, Michael, 1843-1928.
Ann Arbor, Michigan businessman, dealer in coal, farm machinery, bicycles, and automobiles; correspondence, letterbooks, and various record books of Ann Arbor business/enterprises owned and established by Michael Staebler and his family including Staebler and Elmer, Michael Staebler and Son, and Staebler and Sons.
8644 Aa 2
13.5 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Mr. and Mrs. Walter P. Staebler and Mr. Herman Staebler (donor no. 2718 ) and came to the library in 1953.
The collection is open for research.
Michael Staebler was born September 7, 1843, in the Staebler homestead on Scio Church Road in Lodi Township, at the intersection of Lodi, Scio, Freedom, and Lima townships. He was the son of Maria Wildt Staebler and Frederick Staebler, who had purchased the land from the United States Government in 1831. Michael Staebler had a sawmill, a cider press, and a flax seed press. He also operated a threshing machine.
In 1885 Michael Staebler erected the Germania Building in Ann Arbor on the southeast corner of Ashley and Washington Streets. The American Hotel, now the Earle, occupied part of the building, and the remainder was used to house his various business enterprises. He sold coal, farm machinery, and bicycles. From 1889 to 1891 he was a member of the firm Staebler and Elmer, which manufactured the Ferguson Speed Cart.
Staebler and Son, of which Edward W. was the partner, in 1900, became the first automobile dealers in Ann Arbor. During the next half century they were agents for the Trimoto, the Toledo Steam Carriage, the Winton, the Reo, the Dort, the Franklin, the Oakland, and the Pontiac. The firm name became Staebler and Sons after Michael retired and Herman J. entered the business with Edward. Walter P. Staebler joined them in 1913. The company was dissolved in July, 1952.
As a result of the increasing demand for gasoline, two sons, J. Frederick and Edward W. organized the Staebler Oil Company and became the first independent gasoline distributors in Washtenaw County. Besides Edward, Herman, Walter, and Frederick, who have been mentioned, the children of Michael Staebler were: a daughter who died in infancy, Robert E., Albert H., and Alice Staebler Johnson.
This is a collection of the business papers of Michael Staebler, Ann Arbor businessman, dealer in coal, farm machinery, bicycles and automobiles. The records date from the early 1870s to the late 1920s. Included are some materials of Staebler's son, Edward W., who in addition to assisting in the family business was also active in bicycling craze of the 1890s.
Subjects:
Agricultural machinery.; Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Commerce.; Automobile industry and trade--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Business records--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Coal trade--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Cycling--Michigan.; League of American Wheelmen. Michigan Division.; Michigan and Indiana Retail Coal Association.; Bicycle industry--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Staebler, Edward William, 1872-1946.; Staebler and Elmer.; Staebler and Sons.
- Business records
  The collection consists of a single series of business records with subseries of: Incoming Correspondence, Letterbooks, Coal Business, Bicycle/Automobile Business, Other Records.
  The Incoming Correspondence is arranged by the various names of Staebler firms: Staebler and Elmer, Michael Staebler, Michael Staebler and Son, and Staebler and Sons. The Letterbooks have been arranged chronologically. Where the dates of volumes overlap, the volumes presumably documented different business activities. The Coal Sales Order books have interest for the names of Ann Arbor family dealing with Staebler. The Bicycle and Automobile Business records document the changeover taking place in society as the automobile replaced the carriage and wagon as the principal means of transport. The researcher should note that later records of the Staebler family automobile dealership will be found in the papers of Edward W. Staebler.
  - Incoming Correspondence
    - Staebler and Elmer 1890-1891 (Box 1)
    - Michael Staebler 1887-1910
      - 1887-October 1896 (Box 1)
      - November 1896-October 1901 (Box 2)
      - November 1901-December 1903 (Box 3)
      - January 1904-April 1906 (Box 3)
      - 1910 (Box 4)
      - 1910 (Box 5)
        (continued)
    - Staebler and Sons 1911-1915
      - January 1911-April 1912 (Box 5)
      - May-December 1912 (Box 6)
      - July-December 1915 (Box 6)
  - Letterbooks
    - 1886-1887 (Box 7)
    - 1890-1891 (Box 7)
    - 1890-1892 (Box 7)
    - 1892-1894 (Box 7)
    - 1894 (Box 7)
    - 1894-1895 (Box 7)
    - 1895-1896 (Box 7)
    - 1896-1897 (Box 8)
    - 1897-1902 (Box 8)
    - 1897-1899 (Box 8)
    - 1899-1901 (Box 8)
    - 1901-1903 (Box 8)
    - 1903-1904 (Box 8)
    - 1904-1907 (Box 9)
    - 1907-1909 (Box 9)
    - 1909-1911 (Box 9)
    - 1910-1911 (Box 9)
    - 1911-1912 (Box 9)
    - 1912-1913 (Box 10)
    - 1911-1913 (Box 10)
    - 1913-1917 (Box 10)
    - 1913-1915 (Box 10)
    - 1915-1917 (Box 10)
  - Coal business
    - Coal sales order books 1887-1903, 9 volumes (Box 11)
    - Coal sales order books 1893-1895, 2 volumes (Box 12)
    - Michigan and Indiana Retail Coal Association 1898, 1900-1911 (Box 12)
  - Bicycle/automobile business
    - League of American Wheelmen and related
      - Michigan Division 1894-1896 (Box 13)
      - Michigan Division 1897-1899 (Box 13)
      - Michigan bicycle clubs (Box 13)
      - State divisions (Box 13)
      - Bicycle journals (Box 13)
      - Crescent Bulletins; Facts for Victor Agents (Box 13)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 13)
    - Bicycle sales record book 1893-1898 (Box 13)
    - Bicycle and automobile sales record book 1914-1924 (Box 13)
    - New and used automobile sales record book 1925-1934 (Box 13)
    - Auto sales record book (includes bicycle sales) (Box 14)
  - Other records
    - Articles of agreement and contracts 1878-1908, 9 folders (Box 14)
    - Various account books (mainly for agricultural equipment) 1870s-1880s, 3 volumes (Box 14)
    - Dues books for Ann Arbor German social organizations, 3 volumes (Box 14)